Matteo Blandford

Curriculum Vitae

MatteoBlandford.com

Summary and passions

I was trained in architecture and then typography in London and now I work out of Milan, as a freelance with multiple years of international experience in graphic design, typography, video and animation, content production, webdesign and R+D for companies of all sizes I'm a millennial, a child of the internet, the day I got my first computer at 13, my life changed. I believe that we live in a post-modern medieval age, when paradigms of

beauty and functionality are overrated, where visual communication - and its integration with technology - are the only way forward in the unknown future.

I have never had the patience to wait for something good to happen, instead I have always insisted in creating my own (work) journey with self-initiated projects, collective initiatives and a freelance attitude, often choosing a client rather than accepting any commission.

determined to build a set of skills that allowed me to grasp - and work within - multiple design applications in the totality of the tangible and digital world.

Though my practices range from type design to video making and animation, from advertisement campaigns and digital strategies to branding. I consider myself a typographer and graphic designer, in this order. For an overview of my recent work please see my website.

Work Experience

Freelance [2012-Present]

Design and direction; London, Milan.

Responsible for developing projects on commission, often as part of a larger multidisciplinary group within a task, my career has been primarily based on freelancing offering my services and, with a network of collaborators, to deliver a more complete design package for the online and offline worlds. I follow the commissions from the contractual agreements to the delivery and support for the use of the designs. I specialise in branding and the creation of a coherent visual language for a company: having touched most creative subjects personally I've developed in my experience a sense of practicality and efficiency that is applied for the successful use (after the design stage) of the materials. In the last two year I've been mainly working under the pseudonym $\mathsf{DO}^{\scriptscriptstyle\mathsf{TM}}$ on digital based projects for Casaleggio Associati (Italian digital strategy marketing agency) either for them directly or for their clientele. For the projects I worked on I was responsible for successfully initiating, managing and completing graphic design, video, events and web design commissions, including: an internal re-branding, art-direction, production and creation of the event SUM#01, #02, Philip Morris Italy official website and digital strategy for IQOS, Marittimi awareness campaign for the Moby group (ferries), ASG Superconductors new website and more. Since I have moved to Milan I have also been responsible for the graphic and video design of artist Roberto Coda Zabetta, the new website for the curator Paola Clerico and exhibition design commissions in Rome "Invisible Architecture" (soon to open in Tokyo) curated by Rita Elvira Adamo, and in Venice in occasion of the 2018 Architecture Biennale.

Politecnico of Milan [2016-19]

Teaching Assistant; Milan.

Responsible for assisting students on the course: "Laboratorio di Disegno", a first year module of the Fashion Faculty. The module focuses on drawing techniques, design analysis and the development of small fashion collections. I was in charge of two lectures: Using China Ink Pen and The basics of Photoshop, Illustrator and InDesign.

The Northern Block [2016, Internship] Type Designer; Newcastle Upon Tyne.

Responsible for the type design and development of "Auntie"

Responsible for the type design and development of "Auntle a low contrast serif text font inspired by modern typefaces from eighteenth century England and Italy.

UNIT+Collective ltd. [2012-2016]

Co-Founder, Senior Designer; London.

Responsible for successfully initiating, managing and completing projects focused on the social impact of architecture, and expanding the business with graphic design commissions. I initiated and managed the relationship with the local council and partners of Operazione Arcevia, the main project of the collective, which focused on the design and creation of temporary installations and the organisation and management of summer workshops. I was also in charge of the branding, graphic design, web design and the social media presence of UNIT-Collective and Operazione Arcevia. I was the project manager of "LIVE Palazzo", a community regeneration strategy, part of Operazione Arcevia. The project participated to Setup Contemporary Art Fair [2015].

Owl Vision Concepts ltd. [2013-2014]

In-House Graphic Designer; Hong Kong.

Responsible for restoring the company's image and rebranding; I designed and created a solid web-presence for its network of brands, including the production of all the photographic media for catalogues, e-commerce portals and market-specific on-line advertisements. The company was an FMCG eyewear producer with clients across south-east Asia; it has now ceased operations.

Panopus Printing PRS ltd. [2013]

Printing Specialist; London.

Responsible for art and architecture printing commissions, interacting with clientele and achieving the best quality.

Public Works Group ltd. [2011-2012]

Architectural Assistant; London.

Responsible for digital 3D model development, CAD construction detail drawings.

Valentina Marella Photography [2011]

Photographic + Studio Assistant; London.

Responsible for assisting in the production, development and making of fashion photoshoots. The company has now ceased operations.

Movement for Hope [2011, Internship] Public Relations + Social Media; London (UK).

L'albero di Momo [2008-2010]

English teacher: Como.

Notable projects

SUM#01 and #02 [2017-Present]

With: Casaleggio Associati (marketing and digital stategy)
Roberto Coda Zabetta (artist), Francesca Maltese (architect),
Codex Naturae (music production).

In honour of Gianroberto Casaleggio, founder of political group Movimento 5 Stelle, the association created in his name organises each year a day in Ivrea (Italy) dedicated at debating about the future, with panels ranging from medicine to robotics, from politics to energy and more. As $\mathrm{DO^{TM}}$ I am responsible for the creation of the format, event interior design and graphic design, the production of the opening video and the stage direction for the day. In occasion of this project two typefaces were created: Rough, a programmed typewriter font which emulates rough printing, OONE a bitmap dingbat font for the iconography of the event.

Marittimi [2018-Present]

With: Casaleggio Associati (marketing and digital stategy) Roberto Coda Zabetta (artist), Henrik Blomqvist (architect), and Jacek Kubas (programmer). In charge of the brand formatting, graphic design and video editing, website design and printed advertisements, developed from the conceptualisation to delivery with marketing support from Casaleggio Associati. For the client Moby, Tirrenia, Toremar and Onorato Armatori group.

I FURIOSI [2017-Present]

With: Casaleggio Associati and Jacek Kubas (programmer). Graphic identity and brand design with video editing and animation, format design for social media applications. I FURIOSI are a group of influencers dedicated at raising awareness of less harmful alternatives to sigarettes.

Education

University of the Arts London, UK [2015] London College of Communication, MA Contemporary Typographic Media: Distinction (A)

Technical Skills

Excellent use of **Mac** and **Windows** native programs. **Adobe Creative Suite:** Photoshop, Illustrator, Indesign, Lightroom, Acrobat (Interactive PDF), Bridge.

Roberto Coda Zabetta [2013-Present]

Contemporary artist, formerly A. Mondino assistant. I am responsible for the website design, graphic design for the communication of his exhibitions and most recent projects CANTIERI. Video editor and animator for the teaser trailers.

Data Justice Lab [2018]

With: Virginia Ratti (Illustrator). In charge of the brand formatting and new website illustrations, developed from the conceptualisation of the research the lab produces on data. For the University of Cardiff Faculty of Journalism.

Codex Naturæ [2016-Present]

Co-founder in charge of art direction, graphic identity, motion graphics, album cover design, online marketing material and website design for techno Record Label.

La Rivoluzione delle Seppie [2016-Present]

Architecture collective and research group with support from London Metropolitan University and European funding, with focus on refugee integration in Amantea and Belmonte Calabro, Calabria. Co-founder in charge of art direction, logo design, graphic identity, animation, web design, type design, poster series design, book design, illustrations and strategy design. Collateral Event at the Venice Architecture Biennale 2016.

it's easy! unipersonale [2015-Present]

With: Virginia Ratti (illustrator) Alessandro Poletti (programmer). Formerly L'albero di Momo, it is a network of early years English academy schools and teacher training centers, in Como, Lecco, Turin, Milan (ITA), Lugano (CH). Most recently in charge of the production of

London Metropolitan University, UK [2010-2013] The CASS School of Art, Architecture and Design, Architecture BA (Hons) RIBA Part 1: Upper Second-Class Honours (2.1)

Type Design Software: Glyphs, Fontlab, Open type. Video Editing Software: Final Cut Pro 7. Microsoft Office Suite: Word, Excel, Powerpoint.

teaching material and development of the digitalisation of the company - started in late 2018, a designed process towards an e-learning platform in a five year period. My responsibilities are art direction, graphic identity, type design, motion graphics, book design, illustration, billboard advertisement and online marketing campaigns, teaching materials, promotional material design and web design.

Invisible Architecture Exhibition [2017]

Graphic identity of the exhibition, animation and catalogue. Itinerant exhibition on Italian and Japanese architectural movements of the 60s and 70s and the contemporary debate, at Museo Carlo Bilotti, Rome (ITA). Tokyo opening 2019.

Kaleido Music [2016-2017]

Album cover designs and events poster design. Record Label, Milan (ITA).

Innext [2016]

Logotype design for "Together Harambee". Educational project in Kenya, partnering with Google for education and Fondazione Harambee.

MAMMAMIA ltd. [2016]

Branding and type design for Cannabis-infused Italian confectionery producer, Los Angeles (U.S.A.).

Bailey Nelson ltd. [2015]

Mural design for two eyewear stores in London (UK).

Coste Petrai [2014]

Packaging design for a new prosecco line.

More commissions and self initiated projects on request.

Liceo Artistico Bernardino Luini

Cantù, Como, ITA [2006-2010] Diploma Maturità Artistica Quadriennale (Artistic High School Qualification) - 91/100

CAD Software: Vectorworks 2012 (CAD 2D), Autocad 2013, Google Sketchup Pro 8, Artlantis Studio 3. **HTML + CSS**, Web-builders and online insights tools.